ANA SOUSA

Al Research Engineer



Call me: (+351) 926 201 260 **Website:** <u>AMfeta99</u>

Email me: zefinhamaria99@gmail.com

Linkedln: in/ana-maria-sousa-bioeng

Ambitious engineer pursuing my passion and willing to improve. The ideal next step in the career of such a motivated engineer is to contribute to the research and development of technologies that can improve people's lives. I really value being in an international/diverse and innovative environment that encourages the continuous development of personal skills and knowledge.

AWARDS



3rd Place - World Data League 2023

Member of the team 'CEOS'. We finished the international competition in 3rd place among 29 teams of best minds in Data Science.

ML EXPERIENCE :

Machine Learning for Production (MLOPs):

Professional experiencie @Bosch
Projs & repository: <u>MLOPs_Specialization</u>
Training by @Google @TensorFlow @DeepLearning.Al

Computer Vision (CV):

Professional experiencie @InescTech Projs & repository: <u>Advanced_CV</u> Training by @TensorFlow @DeepLearning.AI

Natural language Processing & Large Language models:

Professional experiencie @Utwente
Projs & repository: NLP_LLM
Training by @LAMINI @Google Cloud @AWS @DeepLearning.Al

Generative AI (Gen AI):

Professional experiencie @Utwente
Projs & repository: Master Thesis; NLP_LLM

Training by @LAMINI @Google Cloud @AWS @DeepLearning.Al

Other ML Topics (github repository AMfeta99): Time-series & forecasting; Anomaly detection; Reinforcement Learning, etc...

SKILLS

Languages:

Portuguese (native) English (advanced) Spanish (beginner) Dutch (beginner)

Soft-Skills:

Adaptability
Team communication/work
Problem solver & Proactive
Empathy
Curiosity

Machine Learning Tools:

Data Manipulation (Pandas, Numpy, Scipy)
Machine Learning (Scikit-Sklearn, Tensorflow, Keras)
Prog Languages (Python, Matlab, C++, SQL)

WORK EXPERIENCE



Al Researcher & Solution Developer

2023 - Present (8 months)

воѕсн

- Connected manufacturing project (Sensors, 5G and AI).
- Understand the whole system and provide the appropriate AI algos in the area of Audio processing, MLops, efficient
 Pipeline creation for AI continues learning and deployment

Keywords: MLOps, Abnomaly Detection, Classification, Signal Processing, Tensorflow, Keras



Researcher

2021-2023 (2 years & 2 months)

Section of Cognition, Data and Education | BMS faculty UT | Enschede, NL

- Domain translation of Clinical Neurophysiological research questions/needs into Data Science and ML/DL fields. This
 mediating capacity allowed successful collaboration of CoDE and CNPH groups, boosting the development of project and
 clinical validation
- · Publication of the developed unsupervised and semi-supervised deep learning pipelines for detection of EEG anomalies.
- Implementation and optimization of robust algorithm with a sensitivity of 81.9% and a specificity of 91.7%

Keywords: EEG, Abnomaly Detection, Autoencoder, VAE, VAE-GANs, Diffusion Models, Gen Al, Signal Processing, Tensorflow, Keras,

Researcher intern

Clinical Neurophysiology Group (CNPH) | TechMed Center UT | Enschede, NL

- Review of state-of-the-art approach for captioning in image/signal/video and Inspired on that development, troubleshooting and comparison of **6** pipelines for EEG captioning.
- Presentation and defense of the thesis before a prestigious jury composed of AI and neurologist experts, having obtained the grade of 19/20, result of excellence (among 10% of higher grades).
- Awarded for the performance in the master's thesis "<u>Learning to write medical reports from EEG data</u>." with a job position as Researcher.

Keywords: Attention models, Captioning, Classification, Video, Image, Time-series, Encoder-Decoder, NLP, Numpy, SciPy

Researcher intern

Clinical Neurophysiology Group (CNPH) | TechMed Center UT | Enschede, NL

- Research and implementation of various data augmentation approaches, from traditional signal transformation to more complex data approach, generative models like GANs.
- Proposing and explore the use of different forecasting models for data augmentation.
- Provided important insight into EEG properties and behavior/potential of different approaches, stimulated further research and emergence of new projects.
- Invited to develop a master's thesis at the institution, after obtaining the **Excellent** grade, **19/20** in this Erasmus+ internship, "GANs and Data Augmentation Prediction Models in the Detection of Interictal Epileptiform Discharges (IEDs)".

Keywords: Time-series, Biosignal, GANs, CNN, LSTM / GRU and hybrid models.



Summer Internship

2020-2021 (6 months)

Final Grade: 19 / 20 (A)

Final Grade: 19 / 20 (A)

Visual Computing and Machine Intelligence Group | INESC Technology and Science | Porto, PT

- Impact of facial dynamic fusion information and DBN in the performance of Drowsiness detector (AUTOMOTIVE project.)
- Collaboration with other master and PhDs students for the development of robust Drowsiness detector system to detect driver fatigue.

Keywords: Computer Vision, Facial dynamic fusion, DBN, OpenCV, Scikit-learn

Researcher intern

Biomedical Imaging Lab from C-BER | INESC Technology and Science | Porto, PT

· Characterized lesions associated with lung cancer, using an annotated computed tomography dataset.

Keywords: CT scans, Neural networks, Computer Vision, Image Segmentation

EDUCATION



ERASMUS+ Internship

Institution: Faculty of Science and Technology, University of Twente February 2022 to August 2022 February 2021 to July 2021



Bachelor & Master in Bioengineering - Biomedical Engineering

FEUP PACULADO DE ENCIPHARIA Institution: Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto

2017 - 2022 Final Grade: 18 / 20 (A)

HOBBIES

Member:

2021-2022



Institution: IEEE student Branch

Member of IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology. Organize workshops, and collaborate in the development of EMBS projects together with other students

Volunteer staff:



2022- 202

<u>Tankstation:</u> Multicultural foundation with sociocultural meeting place that organizes and promotes musical, artistic and cultural activities and prepares food from around the world.



<u>Green Vibration:</u> Event organization & Bartender in a truly unique music festival with it's own distinct identity with 3000 attendees and multiple stages in 10 years time.

Sports:

Swimming (federated athlete)

2009 - 2014

Athletics (federated athlete)

2013 - 2019

Dance (Lindy hop)
2023 - Present

OTHER INTERESTS

Music; Dance; Robotics; Psychology